טוב tov today's דף daf is נ"ג nun gimel we pick up
at the bottom of נ"ב עמוד ב' nun bet amud bet and
we're in the middle of discussing the שמחת בית השואבה simchas beis
hashoeva and we're about ten lines from the bottom. תנא tanna גובה
של מנורה חמישים אמה gova shel menora chamishim ama we're talking about
the height of the candelabra that they had in order to light
for the שמחת בית השואבה simchas beis hashoeva these huge candelabra fifty
אמה ama tall like the tree from which they hung המן haman
i guess. so the גמרא gemara and it says that there were
four young כהנים kohanim who would go up on four ladders and
each one it says וארבעה ילדים שפרחי כהונה v'arba yeladim shepirchei kehuna
and the four young
and then it goes on to say וארבעה ילדים שפרחי כהונה v'arba
yeladim shepirchei kehuna four young men of the כהנים kohanim ובידיהם כדי
שמן של מאה ועשרים לוג uveyadeihem kadei shemen shel me'ah v'esrim log
and carrying pitchers of a hundred and twenty לוג log which we
figured out was how many gallons? i don't know thirteen fourteen thirteen
fourteen gallons. ואיבעיא להו v'ibaya l'hu says the גמרא gemara they asked
the question מאה ועשרים לוג כולהו או דילמא לכל חד וחד? me'ah
v'esrim log kulhu o dilma l'chol chad v'chad? ah that would make
it a little bit more reasonable. was it a hundred and twenty
לוג log per person or for all of them together? also that
all of them together it'd be more reasonable that'd only be about
forty לוג log per person maybe about three four gallons five gallons
at most that would be manageable. תא שמע tashma come hear ובידיהם
כדי שמן של שלושים שלושים לוג uveyadeihem kadei shemen shel shloshim shloshim
log we have a ברייתא braisa that says that each one only
had thirty לוג log so the hundred and twenty was the sum
total okay so that makes it manageable שכולם מאה ועשרים לוג she'kulam
me'ah v'esrim log which all combined is a hundred and twenty
לוג. log. תנא tanna we learned in the ברייתא braisa והם משובחים
היו יותר מבנה של מרתא בת פייתוס v'hem meshubachim hayu yoseir mibnasha
mirta bas paitos they were more praiseworthy but it means like stronger
here in the specific context than
the son of
מרתא בת פייתוס. Martha bat Boethus. אמרו על בנה של מרתא בת
פייתוס amru al bnasha d'mirta bas paitos they said about the son
of מרתא בת פייתוס Martha bat Boethus so right the mother the
woman is in the middle here שהיה נוטל שתי יריכות של שור
הגדול shehaya notel shtei yerechot shel shor hagadol he would take the
two thighs of a huge
ox שלקוחה באלף זוז she'lakucha b'elef zuz that would cost a thousand
זוז zuz so it would be a huge ox and he'd take
two thighs of this huge ox ומהלך עקב בצד גודל umehaleich ekev
b'tzad godal and he would walk up the ramp to offer them
up for like an עולה ola you know putting the heel of
one foot by the toe by the big toe of the next
so he'd take tiny little steps you know if you're carrying a
huge thing you want to take wider steps so that you have
a what is it lower center of gravity you have more stability.
he was able to take these two huge thighs of a huge
cow and walk tiny little steps up the ramp.
okay ולא הניחוהו אחיו הכהנים לעשות כן v'lo hinitzhu achav hakohanim la'asot
kein and his brother כהנים kohanim did not let him do that
he thought he was like going to be a big shot and
show what he could do and they said i'm sorry you can't
do that משום ברוב עם הדרת מלך mishum b'rov am hadrat melech
the greater number of people is the greater glory to the king
because you right remember our discussions from יומא yoma about how you
would have one you know you would not have one person taking
two thighs obviously that would be unrealistic you know so the normal
they would normally divide it amongst more כהנים kohanim but he wanted
to show how strong he was he wanted to do you know
this enormous amount all by himself they did not allow it they
demanded that it be divided appropriately. anyway so the גמרא gemara says
מאי משובחים mai meshubachim in what way were these כהנים kohanim who
took the oil you know greater stronger? אילימא משום יוקרא eileima mishum
yukra if it's because of the weight that what they carried was
heavier than what he carried that's not true. הני יקירי טפי hani
yakiri tfei that the thighs of a huge ox are much weightier
than whatever thirty לוג log of oil weighs. so אלא התם כבש
ומרובע ולא זקיף ela hasham kevesh u'meruba v'lo zakif no the difference
is
there it was a ramp and it was squared meaning like at
an angle and not perpendicular. הכא סולמות וזקיף
טובא hacha sulamot v'zakif tuva here they were ladders and they were
very perpendicular. so it might be that it weighed less but it
was actually much more challenging going almost direct vertically up with that
weight than it was walking up a lower a lower inclined ramp
yes charlie.
wasn't מרתא בת פייתוס Martha bat Boethus the wife of יהושע בן
גמלא Yehoshua ben Gamla the high priest? yes
so why didn't it say יהושע בן גמלא Yehoshua ben Gamla's son
that would even be more
yeah that's an interesting
point because it shows the daughter of מרתא בת פייתוס Martha bat
Boethus married יהושע בן גמלא. Yehoshua ben Gamla. yes she married יהושע
בן גמלא Yehoshua ben Gamla
and he became כהן גדול. kohen gadol.
oh
maybe i maybe it was daughter from a previous marriage maybe she
was an אלמנה almana oh no that couldn't be then she'd be
an אלמנה almana and she couldn't marry a כהן גדול. kohen gadol.
maybe it was after the כהן גדול kohen gadol died and she
was married to follow?
he was יהושע בן גמלא Yehoshua ben Gamla was very late very
very late just a few years before the קרבן korban
i don't know you got me good question impressive. Excellent question. All
right. ולא היה חצר בירושלים. Velo haya chatzer bi'Yerushalayim.
It said in the משנה Mishna there was no courtyard in Jerusalem
that was not lit up from the light of the שמחת בית
השואבה. Simchat Beit HaShoeivah. So the גמרא Gemara obviously, you know, was
on הר הבית, Har HaBayit, so it was pretty high. Nevertheless, as
we said, it does sound like some of this is an exaggeration.
Anyway, תניא... Tanya... תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, top of מ"ג ע"א. Mem
Gimmel Amud Aleph. אישה היתה בוררת חיטים לאור שמחת בית השואבה. Isha
hayta boreret chitim le'or Simchat Beit HaShoeivah.
A woman would choose out... would be able to like, you know,
select grain,
wheat, you know, by the light of the שמחת בית השואבה. Simchat
Beit HaShoeivah. So, you know, you could sift your grain and you
could find the tiny little, you know, pieces of chaff that you
need to throw away with such a good light. All right. חסידים
ואנשי מעשה. Chasidim ve'anshei ma'aseh.
So it says the righteous person and people of acts of, you
know, good deeds would... the משנה Mishna goes on to say, what
does it say that they would do? They were the ones that
would be juggling the... yeah, they would be the ones that would
be dancing and juggling the torches and saying words of song and
praise. Okay. And then it says the לויים Levi'im would be playing
the musical instruments. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. We taught a ברייתא. Braita.
יש מהם אומרים. Yesh mehem omerim. There were those that would say:
אשרי ילדותנו שלא ביישה את זקנותנו. Ashrei yaldutenu shelo biysha et ziknutenu.
Praise is our youth that it did not give us shame in
our old age. So meaning that we were good guys even from
when we were young. We never... we're never embarrassed about our deeds
of youth. אלו חסידים ואנשי מעשה. Elu chasidim ve'anshei ma'aseh. Those are
the righteous and those of good deeds that, you know, were always
righteous. ויש מהם אומרים, Ve'yesh mehem omerim, and some of the people
that would do the dancing would say:
אשרי זקנותנו שכפרה על ילדותנו. Ashrei ziknutenu she'kapra al yaldutenu. Praise is
our old age that it atoned for our wild youth.
ואלו בעלי תשובה. Ve'elu ba'alei teshuva. These are those that have repented,
people that had a wilder youth and now are and now are
righteous. אלו ואלו אומרים. Elu va'elu omerim. Those and those say: אשרי
מי שלא חטא, Ashrei mi shelo chata, praise is the one who
has never sinned, ומי שחטא ישוב וימחול לו, u'mi shechata yashuv ve'yimchol
lo, and the one who has sinned should repent and it will
be good for him. How exactly that fits with the idea of,
you know,
במקום שבעלי תשובה עומדין צדיקים גמורים אינם יכולים לעמוד, Be'makom she'ba'alei teshuva
omdin tzadikim gemurim einam yecholim la'amod, but all that being said, it's
better never to have sinned. Okay. Now, תניא. Tanya. We taught in
a ברייתא. Braita. אמרו עליו על הלל הזקן. Amru alav al Hillel
HaZaken. They said about הלל Hillel the Elder, כשהיה שמח בשמחת בית
השואבה, keshehaya same'ach be'Simchat Beit HaShoeivah, when he would rejoice in the
rejoicing of the שמחת בית השואבה, Simchat Beit HaShoeivah, אמר כן, amar
ken, this is what he would say: אם אני כאן הכל כאן.
im ani kan hakol kan. If I'm here, then everyone is here.
ואם איני כאן מי כאן? ve'im eini kan mi kan? And if
I'm not here, then who's here? No one. It sounds a little...
it sounds a little arrogant. But as we'll see in a minute,
he seems to be talking in the divine voice, like representing God.
By the way, though, if you just pause for a minute and
think about the other famous statement of הלל, Hillel, right? What's the
statement of הלל Hillel that everybody loves to quote? אם אין אני
לי מי לי וכשאני לעצמי מה אני. Im ein ani li mi
li u'keshe'ani le'atzmi mah ani. Right? If I'm not for myself, who
will be for me? But if I'm only for myself, what good
am I? So that at least is like a balanced statement. That
means like, okay, you have to care about yourself because, you know,
at the end of the day, you're the only one who cares
most about you, but you're not only supposed to care about yourself.
What good are you if you're self-serving? You're supposed to be there,
you know, care about other people. But this doesn't have the balance.
This is just like repeating the same thing in a different way.
If I'm here, everyone's here. And if I'm not here, then who
needs... who cares who else is here? It's just... just repeating the
same thing. So it's going to seem like he's talking here basically,
as I said, in God's voice. If you take a look at
רש"י, Rashi, three lines from the top: אם אני כאן הכל כאן.
im ani kan hakol kan. דורש היה לרבים שלא יחטאו בשמו של
הקדוש ברוך הוא, Doresh haya lerabbim shelo yechete'u bishmo shel HaKadosh Baruch
Hu, that they should... so he was teaching the masses and like
in the name of God, speaking as if God were speaking. אם
אני כאן הכל כאן. im ani kan hakol kan. כל זמן שאני
חפץ בבית הזה ושכינתי שרויה בו. Kol zman she'ani chafetz babayit hazeh
u'shchinati sruya bo. As long as I desire this house and my
presence dwells in it, יהיה כבודו קיים, yihiye kevodo kayam,
its glory will remain, ויבוא הכל כאן. ve'yavo hakol kan. And if
I'm here, everybody will come here. ואם תחטאו ואסלק שכינתי, Ve'im techete'u
ve'asallek shchinati, but
if you sin and my presence departs, מי יבוא כאן? mi yavo
kan? Who will come here? Meaning, so that's actually, you know, an
important thing. Here everybody is the rejoicing, partying, having a great time.
It's easy to like lose sight of the fact that it's not
just, wow, this is a great place for like everybody to gather,
you know, it's... but the point of this place is God's presence.
It's actually interesting, I think we mentioned this, we mentioned this yesterday.
I think we did. Anyway, you know, the role that a בית
כנסת beit knesset plays, right? Going way back, it's played... it's always
played a double function, right? A בית כנסת, beit knesset, a place
of gathering, and like a מקדש מעט, mikdash me'at, a place of
representing God's place and of prayer and of and of worship and
so on. So here where really it is... it's the רגל, regel,
everybody's gathering, everybody's partying, you're not even bringing קרבנות, korbanot, so, you
know, it's sort of like he's saying, hey, you know, this is
about God's presence. So if I'm here, then everybody is here. Everybody
comes. If I'm not here... So here where it is, it doesn't
matter, mi kan מי כאן? mi kan? Like what's worth it that
what I even everybody being here? So what matters here is God's
presence. Okay. So, who haya omer הוא
היה אומר, who haya omer, he used to say, who haya omer
ken הוא היה אומר כן. who haya omer ken. You'd say the
following: Lemakom she'ani ohev, sham raglai molichot oti למקום שאני אוהב, שם
רגלי מוליכות אותי. lemakom she'ani ohev, sham raglai molichot oti. The place
that I love, there my legs will bring me. Okay, a little
interesting. So we'll see what that means. Sounds like now he's not
talking about God, raglai רגלי, raglai, but let's look at the next
lines. Im tavo el beiti, ani avo el beitecha אם תבוא אל
ביתי, אני אבוא אל ביתך. im tavo el beiti, ani avo el
beitecha. If you come to my house, I'll come to your house.
We have a playdate with me, then we'll have a playdate with
you. But he's not exactly talking about playdates. Im atah lo tavo
el beiti, ani lo avo el beitecha אם אתה לא תבוא אל
ביתי, אני לא אבוא אל ביתך. im atah lo tavo el beiti,
ani lo avo el beitecha. If you don't come to my house,
I won't come to your house. Again, seemingly talking in God's name,
not like saying to God, God, if you come to my house,
then I'll come visit the Beit HaMikdash בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. Presumably,
it's the opposite point. God is speaking and saying, if you come
and visit the Beit HaMikdash בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, then I will
also bring my presence into your homes. Shene'emar שנאמר, shene'emar, as the
verse says, bechol hamakom asher azkir et shemi בכל המקום אשר אזכיר
את שמי, bechol hamakom asher azkir et shemi, wherever I call my
name to be mentioned, avo elecha uverachticha אבוא אליך וברכתיך, avo elecha
uverachticha, I will come and bless you. So I will come and
bless you in your own homes if you first come to my
house. By the way, that plays nicely into the theme of Sukkot
סוכות, Sukkot, which is about, sort of, you know, the sukkah סוכה
sukkah as a house, but it's also about that intersection. The sukkah
סוכה sukkah both is being the house and sort of God's presence,
ananei kavod ענני כבוד, ananei kavod, the Mikdash מקדש Mikdash metaphors and
imagery of the sukkah סוכה. sukkah. So the bringing together of God's
house and being in God's presence in God's house, but then also
God's presence in our house. Okay. So you come to my house,
you have this rejoicing or whatever, then I will also be present
for you in your house. What is this issue about the place
where I want to go? Okay. So Rashi רש"י Rashi says, one
minute...
one minute...
okay,
sorry. So it's not exactly clear what that first part about it
was. One imagines that it's somewhat related to the idea of aliyah
l'regel עליה לרגל, aliyah l'regel, right? It says, right, where was it?
Lemakom she'ani ohev, sham raglai molichot oti למקום שאני אוהב, שם רגלי
מוליכות אותי, lemakom she'ani ohev, sham raglai molichot oti, that he's probably
talking... otherwise it just seems irrelevant to the whole point, right? I
go where I love. But it's talking presumably the whole idea of
where I go and with my regel רגל, regel, raglai molichot oti
רגלי מוליכות אותי, raglai molichot oti, that it's first sort of talking
in the voice of the Jewish people, that we go, you know,
our legs bring us to the place that we love. We love
being brought, you know, being brought here to the Beit HaMikdash בית
המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, and then God is responding and sort of saying,
well, welcome to my house, and if you come to my house,
I will therefore come into your houses. Okay. So now he continues.
Af hu ra'ah gulgoret achat shetzafah al pnei hamayim אף הוא ראה
גולגולת אחת שצפה על פני המים. af hu ra'ah gulgoret achat shetzafah
al pnei hamayim. He saw, this is now the one that we
know from Pirkei Avot פרקי אבות, Pirkei Avot, he saw a certain
skull that was floating on the water. Amar lah אמר לה, amar
lah, he said to it, oh Horatio, I knew him well—no, sorry.
He said to it, al de'atpacht atpuch, ve'sof mativeych yetufun על דאטפת
אטפוך, וסוף מטיפייך יטופון, al de'atpacht atpuch, ve'sof mativeych yetufun, because you
spilled blood, your blood was
spilled. And those that spilled, or of, you know, or that you
caused another
person... no, Rashi רש"י Rashi doesn't mean that you caused another skull
to float, your skull was made to float, and those that made
your skull float, their skulls will float. Meaning everybody... there's like justice
in the world. Okay. And if this happened to you, must be
that something happened that you deserved it.
Okay. Amar Rabbi Yochanan אמר רבי יוחנן, amar Rabbi Yochanan,
said Rabbi Yochanan. Now picking up the point about my legs bring
me to the place that I love, Rabbi Yochanan has a different
type of a twist on this. Amar Rabbi Yochanan אמר רבי יוחנן,
amar Rabbi Yochanan, said Rabbi Yochanan, ragloi d'bar enash רגלוהי דבר אינש,
ragloi d'bar enash, the legs of a person, inun arvin bei אינון
ערבין ביה, inun arvin bei, they are his guarantors. L'atar d'mitbe'i taman
לאתר דמיתבעי תמן, l'atar d'mitbe'i taman, the place that he is needed,
d'mitbe'i taman movilin yatei דמיתבעי תמן מובילין יתיה, d'mitbe'i taman movilin yatei,
there they bring him. What does this mean? So, not necessarily the
place... so we'll see, it means in terms of guarantors and ensuring
that the debt is paid back. And what debt is paid back?
The debt of your life is paid back to God. So this
is basically a way of saying that you wind up going to
the place you need to go to in order to die. Hanu
tartei Kushaye הנהו תרתי כושיא, hanu tartei Kushaye, there were two Kushim
כושים, Kushim, which Rashi רש"י Rashi says is a euphemism, very,
whatever, the Gemara's
גמרא Gemara's attitude towards Kushim כושים Kushim tended to be negative, and
here Rashi רש"י Rashi claims that it's using it in a way
of saying that they were very beautiful people. But anyway, there is
that obvious bias in the Gemara גמרא. Gemara. Anyway, these two Kushim
כושים Kushim dehavi kaimei kammai deShlomo דהוו קיימי קמי דשלמה, dehavi kaimei
kammai deShlomo, which were in front of Shlomo שלמה. Shlomo. Elihoreph ve'Achiyah
bnei Shisha אליהורף ואחיה בני שישא, Elihoreph ve'Achiyah bnei Shisha,
okay,
that was their names. It's a verse in Melachim מלכים. Melachim. And
they were sofrey deShlomo סופרי דשלמה, sofrey deShlomo, they were Shlomo's שלמה
Shlomo's scribes, havu הוו. havu. Yoma chad chaza lemalech hamavet dehavi ka'atziv
יומא חד חזייה למלאך המות דהוה קא עצב. Yoma chad chaza lemalech
hamavet dehavi ka'atziv. One day he saw the angel of death, Shlomo
שלמה Shlomo saw the angel of death, who was very sad. Amar
lei אמר ליה, amar lei, he said to him... Why are you
so sad? אמר ליה Amar leh *Amar lei*, this reminds me when
I was growing up I used to read those stories in the
Jewish Press, you know, in the center page, what they called, stories
from the תלמוד *Talmud*, something like that. You know those stories, they
always had the שלמה *Shlomo* stories. שלמה *Shlomo* talking to the שדים
*Shedim* and שלמה *Shlomo* talking to the angels. That's what I'm talking
about. They always had the, anyway. Okay, so said why are you
so sad? אמר ליה Amar leh: דקבעו מיני הני תרתי כושי *Amar
lei de-ka bayu minei hani tartei kushi* because I'm being asked to
produce these two כושים *Cushim*, you know, I mean I'm supposed to,
imagine like the Angel of Death there
with his scythe and I have to go ahead and take them
back to, you know, take them to the grave. ויתבי הכא *Ve-yasvi
hakha* and they're sitting here.
So, and, so, so שלמה *Shlomo*, I'm sad because I need to
get to them or whatever, so I'll have to be taking their
lives. So שלמה *Shlomo* heard this and he wanted to protect them.
מסרינהו לשדים *Masrinuhu le-shedim*, so he gave them over to the שדים
*Shedim*, these
כושים *Cushim*. שדרינהו למחוזא דלוז *Shadruhu le-mahoza de-Luz* and he sent them
to the city of לוז *Luz*. To מחוזא דלוז *Mahoza de-Luz*, that's
a good hideout, that's a safe haven. Okay, and also, and in
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* in סוטה sotah. *Sotah* it says that לוז
*Luz* was a place that nobody died, that the Angel of Death
had no dominion over לוז *Luz*. So he figures I'll send them
there, they'll be safe. Okay, כי מטו למחוזא דלוז *Ki matu le-mahoza
de-Luz*, when they came to the city of לוז *Luz*, so שכיבו
*shkhivu*, they died like just at the gates of the city, right
before they walked into the city, they just missed getting into the
safe city. Okay, למחר חזייה למלאך המות דהוה קא בדיח *Le-makhar khaziyei
le-malakh ha-mavet de-hava ka badiya'kh*. So the next day שלמה *Shlomo* saw
the Angel of Death who was laughing. אמר ליה Amar leh, אמאי
בדיחת *Amar lei amai badiya'chas*, why are you laughing? אמר ליה Amar
leh, *Amar lei* or why are you so happy? באתרא דבעו מיני
*Be-asra de-ba'u minei*, the place where I needed to take them, תמן
שדרתינהו *taman shadartinu*, that's where you sent them to. Thank you very
much! I was given a task not just to take their lives
but to take their lives at the outskirts of לוז *Luz* and
you helped arrange for it. Thank you very much!
So, so, where were we? מיד פתח שלמה ואמר *Miyad patach Shlomo
ve-amar*, therefore שלמה *Shlomo* opened up and said, meaning you know opened
his mouth and said, רגלוהי דבר איניש אינון ערבין ביה *raglohi de-var
inish inun arvin beh*, so didn't I bet you didn't know שלמה
*Shlomo* talked Palestinian or whatever or Babylonian Aramaic. So the legs of
a person
they are his guarantors.
לאתרא דמיתבעי תמן מובילין יתיה *Le-asra de-misba'ei taman movilin yatei*, the place
that he is needed, תמן מובילין יתיה *taman movilin yatei*, that's where
they bring him. Okay, anyway that was a digression about this statement
about הלל Hillel. *Hillel*. But it was again interesting in הלל Hillel
*Hillel* this whole idea of coming to God's house and God coming
to our house and not losing sight of the presence of the
שכינה *Shekhinah*, etc. Okay, תני *tani*, we saw in the ברייתא *Braitah*.
אמר amar, להו רבי Rebbi. שמעון בן גמליאל *Amar lehu Rabbi Shimon
ben Gamliel*. They said about רבי Rebbi שמעון בן גמליאל *Rabbi Shimon
ben Gamliel*, כשהיה שמח שמחת בית השואבה Simchas Beis Hashoeva, *keshe-haya some'ach
simchas beis ha-sho'evah*, when he would rejoice at the rejoicing of the
בית השואבה *Beis Ha-sho'evah*, היה נוטל שמונה אבוקות של אור *haya notel
shemoneh avukos shel ur*,
he would take eight torches of light or fire or flame, וזורק
אחת
ונוטל אחת *ve-zorek achas ve-notel achas*, throw one, catch the next, ואין
נוגעות זו
בזו *ve-ein nog'os zu be-zu*,
and they wouldn't touch one another, they'd be in a perfect circle
and not and he would juggle them without any one even hitting
into the next. וכשהוא משתחוה *Ve-khishehu mishtachaveh*, and then he did a
type of a prostration, השתחויה *hishtachavayah*, ונועץ שני גודליו בארץ *ve-no'etz shenei
gudlav ba-aretz*,
he put his two thumbs on the ground,
so not his flat palms, but you know imagine trying to do
a pushup basically with just your thumbs on the ground, not the
flat of your palms, he would put his two thumbs on the
ground, ושוחה ונושק את הרצפה *ve-shocheh ve-noshek es ha-ritzpah*, and he'd bend
down and he would kiss the ground, again like you know as
flat like again like a type of a pushup type of a
mode, וזוקף *ve-zokef*
and then he push himself back up, ואין כל בריה יכולה לעשות
כן *ve-ein kol beryah yacholah la'asos kein*, and nobody else could do
this. I see some guys at the gym, I don't know, maybe
I think they might be able to. Anyways, וזו היא קידה *ve-zu
hi kida*, and this is called קידה *Kida*, a type of way
of prostration which is obviously extremely difficult. לוי אחוי קידה *Levi achvi
kida*, לוי *Levi*
demonstrated how to do a קידה *Kida*, קמיה דרבי *kamei de-Rabbi*, in
the presence of רבי *Rabbi*, this was after the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash *Beis Ha-mikdash* but he was showing what is this thing called
a קידה *Kida*, ואיטלא *ve-itla*,
and he became lame, he so he he got you know injured
in a in a you know in a serious way as a
result. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, ומה גרמא ליה *ve-ha garma
lei*, is that what caused him to become lame? דאמר רבי אלעזר
*De-amar Rabbi Elazar*, doesn't רבי אלעזר *Rabbi Elazar* say, לעולם אל יטיח
אדם דברים כלפי מעלה *le-olam al yati'ach adam devarim klapei ma'alah*, a
person should never cast words to heaven, meaning sort of you know
complaining to God. שהרי אדם גדול הטיח דברים כלפי מעלה ואיטלא *She-harei
adam gadol hitich devarim klapei ma'alah ve-itla*, for there was a great
person that cast words against God and he became lame, ומנו לוי
*u-manu Levi*, and that was לוי *Levi*. So,
so what was the word he cast against God? If you look
at רש"י Rashi *Rashi*, he quotes the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* in תענית
*Ta'anis* first wide line, עלית וישבת לך במרום ואינך משגיח על בניך
*alisa ve-yashavta lach ba-marom ve-eincha mashgi'ach al banecha*, God, you've taken presence
up in heaven and you're not paying attention to what's happening to
your children. Of course there goes all the great חסידיש *Chasidish* stories,
right? All those great חסידיש *Chasidish* stories, who was it, רבי לוי
יצחק מברדיטשוב *Rabbi Levi Yitzchak m'Berditchev*'s stories, right, where he would say,
you know, where he'd... basically has his complaints to God. What was
some of those good ones? He said, God let's have a look,
what was it, it's like I know we've done all these sins
and we've done all these wrong things, but let me tell you
what you've done wrong. And it would list all the bad things
that happened to the Jews. Tell you what, why don't we just
call it even?
Anyway, all right, so Levi did that apparently, and they were not
happy with him that he did that, and he became lame. So
the גמרא Gemara says, so isn't that why he became lame? So
the גמרא Gemara. says,
הא והא גרמו ליה. Ha veha garmu lei. Yeah, they both contributed.
Meaning, okay, so he did something that was deserving of punishment, but
then he had to actually try, go ahead and demonstrate this קדה
kida that actually was the proximate cause of him becoming lame. All
right. Now, now that we're talking about
Levi, לוי הוה מטייל קמי דרבי בתמני סכיני. Levi hava metayel kamei
d'Rebbi b'tamnei skinei. So Levi would sort of be,
you know, would sort of like juggle eight knives. Literally says he
would walk in front of רבי. But רש״י Rashi says, קמי דרבי
בביתו שהיה נשיא ומכבדין אותו בשמחה. Kamei d'Rebbi beveiso shehaya Nasi umichabdin
oso b'simcha. So this isn't שמחת בית השואבה, Simchas Beis Hashoeva? but
some type of a similar type of a joy now that they
did in רבי'ס Rebbi's house on his behalf. Interesting, רש״י Rashi says,
שהיה דואג תמיד בצרת ישראל ובכל יד, Shehaya do'eg tamid b'tzaras Yisrael
u'vechol yad, יום דמחייך ביה רבי אתי פורענות לעולם. Yoma demichaich bei
Rebbi asi puranus l'olam.
So רבי was the one whose job it was to worry about
כלל ישראל. Klal Yisrael. So Levi was somehow trying, cheering him up,
and Levi juggled with knives, the same Levi who became lame. I
assume this was before he before he became lame, but he was
sort of certainly liked tempting fate or, you know, taunting
danger. Anyway, בתמני סכיני, B'tamnei skinei, eight knives.
שמואל Shmuel קמי דשבור מלכא בתמני מזגי חמרא. Kamei de'Shvor Malka b'tamnei
mazgei chamra. שמואל Shmuel would juggle with eight cups of, eight glasses
of wine. Can you possibly juggle a glass of wine without it
spilling? Has anybody ever seen that?
I have never seen that.
I mean, people can juggle torches and juggle knives, but I don't
just understand the physics of how you could juggle a glass of
wine without it without it, okay. Anyway, okay.
אביי Abaye קמי דרבא Kamei de'Raba would, let's say, בתמניא ביעי, B'tamneya
beyei, eight eggs, I assume raw eggs. That's a little bit safer.
Okay, so if you want to try to practice some fancy juggling,
don't use knives or torches; eggs will just make a mess. ואמרי
לה בארבעה ביעי, V'amri lah b'arba'ah beyei, and some would say four
eggs. So things are getting a little bit more realistic. You know,
it's like you read הסדורות. Hasdoros. Basically, what it is, it goes
from fire to knives to eggs, eight to four, so you read
הסדורות. Hasdoros. רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan juggling in the ישיבה? Yeshiva? Yeah,
I know. Although I can do a demonstration of juggling. You want
to see a demonstration of juggling in honor of the שמחת בית
השואבה? Simchas Beis Hashoeva. I don't know if I can do these,
they are different weights. All right. If they were the same weight,
I could do it better. Thank you, thank you. That's my שמחת
בית השואבה. Simchas Beis Hashoeva. Okay, that's, I mean, you know. תניא
אמר רבי יהושע בן חנניה כשהיינו שמחים שמחת בית השואבה. Tanya, amar
Rebbe Yehoshua Ben Chananya, kshehayinu smeichim Simchas Beis Hashoeva. Back to שמחת
בית השואבה. Simchas Beis Hashoeva When we would do that, לא ראינו
שינה בעינינו. lo ra'inu sheina b'eineinu. Our eyes would not see sleep.
We'd be up the whole night. Okay. כיצד שעה ראשונה תמיד של
שחר. Keitzad? Sha'ah rishonah Tamid shel Shachar. The first hour of the
day, sunrise being the morning שחרית. Shacharit. משם לתפילה. Misham litfillah.
Then time for דאוונען. davening. משם לקרבן מוסף. Misham l'korban Musaf. Then
we'd go to be present at the קרבן מוסף. Korban Musaf. משם
לתפילת המוספין. Misham litfillas hamusafin.
Then דאוון מוסף. daven Musaf. Then דאוון מוסף. daven Musaf. משם לבית
המדרש. Misham l'Beis Hamedrash.
Then we would go and we'd spend the afternoon studying. We'd go
into the בית מדרש. Beis Hamedrash. משם לאכילה ושתיה. Misham l'achilah ushtiyah.
Or late morning studying. Then we would eat. משם...
it's quite fascinating, by the way, it doesn't say משם לסוכה. Because
if you're eating and drinking, presumably you're doing it in a סוכה.
Sukkah. It is סוכות. Succos. But the סוכה Sukkah isn't getting mentioned
here. Okay. משם לתפילת המנחה. Misham litfillas hamincha.
Then it's time to דאוון מנחה. daven Mincha. משם לתמיד של בין
הערבים. Misham l'tamid shel bein ha'arbayim. Then it's time for the afternoon
קרבן. Korban. מכאן ואילך. Mikan va'eilach. And once the afternoon קרבן Korban
was over, the קרבנות korbanos of the day was over, לשמחת בית
השואבה. l'Simchas Beis Hashoeva. We'd start the whole rejoicing of the שמחת
בית השואבה Simchas Beis Hashoeva. which would last till the next morning
and then we'd do the whole thing all over again. So we
would never go to sleep because then we'd just, you know, we'd
go through the night with our שמחת בית השואבה. Simchas Beis Hashoeva?
Of course the גמרא Gemara says, is that really possible?
ואיני והאמר רבי יוחנן שבועה שלא אישן שלשה ימים מלקין אותו וישן
לאלתר. Ve'eini? Ve'amar Rebbe Yochanan, shevuah shelo ishan shlosha yamim, malkin oso
v'yashen l'alsar. If somebody takes an oath that they won't sleep for
seven days, for three days even, you give him lashes because it's
a false oath, it's an impossible thing to do to go three
days without sleeping, and then he can sleep right away because the
oath wasn't binding at all. So even three days is impossible, and
here you're talking about, what, five, six days? אלא הכי קאמר לא
טעמנו טעם שינה. Ela hachi ka'amar: Lo ta'amnu ta'am sheina. We never
really had the taste of sleep, meaning, you know, you got a
little nap, you never really got a good געשמאק geshmak sleep in.
דהוו מנמנמי אכתפי דהדדי. Dahavu minamnamai akatfei d'hadadi. We would sort of
like doze off on one another's shoulders, but we never actually got
an opportunity to take a real nap while we were at this
time. Okay. חמש עשרה מעלות. Chamesh esrei ma'alos. Fifteen. I was going
to see if I could show, demonstrate some juggling for you. Shall
I demonstrate some juggling in honor of the שמחת בית השואבה? Simchas
Beis Hashoeva. I don't know if I can do these, they are
different weights.
All right. If they were the same weight, I could do it
better. Thank you, thank you. That's my שמחת בית השואבה. Okay, that's,
I mean, you know. Clearly rabbis have to learn how to do
that as we could see. All right, so the גמרא Gemara. continues.
All right, אמר ליה Amar lei, so 15 steps. אמר
ליה רב חסדא להו מדרבנן. Amar leh Rav Chisda lehu miderabbanan. So
there were 15 steps, you know, from the עזרת ישראל Ezras Yisrael
to the עזרת נשים, Ezras Nashim, the לויים Levi'im would stand on
that steps. רש"י Rashi points out that that's not what they would
stand with the קרבן korban because that's outside of the עזרה, Azarah,
but it was corresponding to the 15 שירי המעלות shirei hama'alos and
that's where they would stand. Like it says, like you know you
got the band up in front, they're going to be leaving from
the front door way over to the east in the עזרת נשים.
Ezras Nashim. This is way over to the west where the עזרת
נשים Ezras Nashim goes up into עזרת ישראל. Ezras Yisrael. Okay, so
אמר ליה רב חסדא להו מדרבנן. Amar leh Rav Chisda lehu miderabbanan.
רב חסדא Rav Chisda said to one of the rabbis דהוה קמסדר
אגדתא קמיה dehavah kamsader agaddata kameih that was arranging the אגדתא agaddata
in his presence, meaning that was sort of laying it, sort of
like quoting traditional statements of אגדתא agaddata to be expounded upon.
Where were we?
אמר ליה: שמיע לך הני חמיסר מעלות כנגד מי אמרן דוד? Shemia
lach hani chamisar ma'alos keneged mi amaran David? Have you heard that
these 15 שירי המעלות, shirei hama'alos, what do they correspond to? Because
here's somebody who really knows אגדתא agaddata and he's got a whole
storehouse of אגדתא agaddata like this was the Bar-Ilan before there was
a Bar-Ilan, you know, some of these people had memorized all this
stuff. So he said to him, have you heard a good explanation
about what those 15 שירי המעלות shirei hama'alos correspond to? So אמר
ליה, he said to him: הכי אמר רבי יוחנן, Hachi amar Rabbi
Yochanan, this is what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says: בשעה שכרה דוד
שיתין, Beshah shekarah David shitin, when remember the old שיתין, shitin, those
underground caverns and there were three opinions. One said that they were
a natural formation, one said that they were dug, and a third
explanation that there weren't underground caverns, it was just a hollow in
the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash that was where the wine went after
it was poured on the מזבח. mizbeiach. But according to the assumption
that there were these caverns and that they were dug, here the
גמרא Gemara is saying that they were dug by דוד. David. Okay,
so here's what happens, very famous גמרא. Gemara When דוד David dug
the שיתין, shitin, קפא תהומא, kafa tehoma, he dug a little too
deep and he broke through to the underground depths of water and
they were now coming through the hole that he had dug and
ובעי למישטפיה לעלמא, uvai lemishpeih le'alma, it wanted to flood the world.
You know, he put his shovel a little bit too deep and
pshhh, all the water is now coming out from way deep down
and now it's going to completely flood the world.
אמר דוד Amar David 15 songs of a מעלות Ma'alos and brought
them back, the water back down to its place. So the גמרא
Gemara said back, אי הכי, ee hachi, if that's true,
15 שירי המעלות, shirei hama'alos, songs of
ascent? אחותי מבעי ליה? Achutei mibai leh? It should be the 15
songs of descent! It should be bringing them down, not bringing them
up! So אמר ליה, he said back to him, the person who
knew the אגדתא: agaddata: אה, ואזכרתן, Ah, ve'izkartan, oh you maybe remember
something. הכי אתמר, Hachi itmar, here's the way it was said. Oh,
that's a good point, I knew I got it wrong. בשעה שכרה
דוד שיתין, Beshah shekarah David shitin, when דוד David dug the שיתין,
shitin, קפא תהומא, kafa tehoma, so the underground depths floated up, burst
forth, ובעי למישטפיה לעלמא, uvai lemishpeih le'alma, and it was about to
flood the world. אמר דוד: Amar David: מי איכא דידע אי שרי
למיכתב שם אחספא? Mi ika deyada ee sharei lemichtav shem achaspa? Is
there anybody who knows whether it's permissible to write the divine name
on a piece of pottery ונשדי בתהומא venishdi bitehoma and we'll throw
it into the depths ומנח umenach and it'll stay there? So actually
this was like when, what was it, BP right?
The puncture through and how do you get down there with all
the oil pouring out and recover the hole. So this is what
they were trying to do. They should have checked this גמרא. Gemara
The גמרא Gemara, had the answer. All you have to do is
write God's name on a piece of pottery and you throw it
down and it'll find its way to the hole and stop up
the hole and that solves the problem. So of course it's funny
that they say on pottery, right? Because pottery floats. You'd have to
say a rock or something. Anyway,
רש"י Rashi says: מפני שחרס צולל ויורד ואינו צף. Mipnei shecheres tzolel
veyored ve'eino tzaf. Is that true? Pottery sinks?
Pottery sinks?
Yeah, it's heavier than water.
Pottery is heavier than water? Okay, fine. Oh, I guess it says
in a note here that it was a special shard. Special shard?
That...
yeah, go on,
what's the explanation?
Well, it just says it was a special shard that was weighty?
No, no, it says... he
suggested using an earthenware shard because earthenware sinks so the shard would
sink down to the opening of the sea but the divine name
was written on it.
Right, so רש"י Rashi, says, and
that's רש"י, Rashi but then there's more, a further... the shard that
דוד David was referring to was not simply any shard, rather when
excavating the pits דוד David discovered a shard on which it was
written that it was in place since the six days
of creation.
By removing this shard דוד David allowed the waters to spray and
this is what דוד David wished
to return to its place.
Right, so that's what רש"י Rashi says. רש"י Rashi, says it wasn't
just he dug too deep, I should have mentioned רש"י, Rashi, it
was you know they were digging and they said "Oh, what's this
piece of pottery here that has God's name? Let's take a look."
And they lifted it up and then phew! Okay. So now they
knew in order to close it back down or whatever. I don't
know if the original piece of pottery had God's name, but it
was there, you know, to close it up, you needed another piece
of pottery now to throw down and to close it up. Okay,
so is it allowed though because it's God's name? It'll lead to
the wearing out of God's name, maybe it's indirect
מחיקת השם, mechikat Hashem,
is it allowed? ומנח לגבי דלא קאמר ליה מידי. u-manach legabei de-la
ka'amar lei midi. Nobody had an answer for him. אמר דוד, Amar
David, it's a little funny here because he got a little like
a פיקוח נפש pikuach nefesh type of thing going on. So David
said, כל היודע לומר ואינו אומר יחנק בגרונו. kol ha-yodeia lomar ve-eino
omer yichanek bi-gerono. Anybody who knows what to say and isn't saying
it, let him be, you know, let him be strangled in his
throat. So נשא אחיטופל קל וחומר בעצמו. Nasa Achitofel kal va-chomer be-atzmo.
So אחיטופל Achitofel made a קל וחומר. kal va-chomer.
He said ומה לעשות שלום בין איש לאשתו, u-ma la'asot shalom bein
ish le-ishto, when it comes to making peace between husband and wife,
אמרה תורה שמי שנכתב בקדושה ימחה על המים, amra Torah shemi shenichtav
bi-kedusha yimacheh al ha-mayim, my name that was written with sanctity should
be scraped into the water to test for the to see if
the woman is a סוטה. So לעשות שלום כל העולם כולו, la'asot
shalom kol ha-olam kulo,
to make peace in the entire world, על אחת כמה וכמה, al
achat kama ve-chama, how much more so should it be
justified. אמר ליה, so he said to him, שרי, shari, it's permissible.
He gave the whole argument, you know, you're in the middle of
a little crisis, just tell me, Okay, it's permissible. So כתב שם
אחספא. ketav shem achaspa. By the way, what's also fascinating though is
that it was only because of like this threat that forced, you
know, אחיטופל Achitofel to like think, like, oh, I don't know anything,
if you don't tell me something, oh wait wait wait, okay yeah,
so okay. So you know, sometimes we need a little external stimulus
to help get our mind moving. Anyway, of course the fact that
the whole world was about to be flooded wasn't enough of a
stimulus. I don't know. Anyway, it's permissible.
נשא אחיטופל קל וחומר בעצמו, Nasa Achitofel kal va-chomer be-atzmo, he did
a quick calculation.
Oh, I right. God said he wasn't going
to, God wasn't, we were about to, anyway, it wasn't by rain.
I don't know. Anyway, permissible. כתב שם אחספא ושדייה לתהומא ונחיה לתהומא.
Ketav shem achaspa ve-shadiyei le-tehoma ve-nacheyei le-tehoma. He wrote a name on
the divine on a
shard and threw it into the depths and the depths went back
down. שיצר שיתסר אלפי גרמידי, Shitzer shiteisar alfei garmidi, but it went
down very very far. It went down sixteen thousand אמות. amot.
So כי חזי דנחית טובא, ki chazi de-nachit tuva, now when someone
saw that it went so far
down, אמר, he said, כמה דמדלי טפי מירטב עלמא, kama de-midlei tefei
mirtav alma, the higher up the depths are closer to the surface,
the more moist the earth is, the more, you know, so it's
better for the world. מירטב עלמא, mirtav alma, the world. אמר חמש
עשרה מעלות דאסקי חמש עשרה אלפי גרמידי. Amar chamesh esreh maalot de-askei
chamesh esreh alfei garmidi. He said the
fifteen songs of ascent that brought back up fifteen out of the
sixteen, sixteen thousand אמות. amot. So אלפי גרמידי, alfei garmidi, thousand אמות.
amot. I'm sorry, I said אמות, amot, thousand. I'm sorry, I said
אמות, amot, thousand אמות. amot. It went down sixteen thousand, שיתסר אלפי
גרמידי, shiteisar alfei garmidi, thousand אמות. amot. He said the fifteen songs
of ascent and it came back up fifteen thousand אמות. amot. ואוקמיה
באלפי גרמידי, Ve-ukmeih be-alfei garmidi, and he had kept it a thousand
אמות amot away from the crust of the earth because, you know,
you don't want it to be too close because then you're going
to get a flood concern. So but so he brought it up
close enough that it should be good for the ground. אמר עולא,
Amar Ulla, said עולא, Ulla, שמע מינה עוביה דארעא אלפי גרמידי. shema
mina ovyah de-ara alfei garmidi. We see that the depths of the
earth is a thousand אמות amot till you hit the תהום tehom
because now that's where the תהום tehom now is. Right, so there's
obviously, so there's obviously clearly what you have here is instead of
a molten core, you've got the understanding of a liquid core. Okay,
so you've got your תהום tehom in the middle which is your
liquid core, right, which is ready to burst forth and then you
have the crust of the earth. So David went down, boom, going
to all flood, sealed it back up. Okay, so then point was
though that it went too far down and then he brought it
back. So now that he brought it back from sixteen thousand אמות
amot to a thousand, he says you see that the
crust of the earth is a thousand אמות, amot, right, because that's
now
where the תהום tehom rests underneath the earth. Okay, so שמע מינה
עוביה דארעא אלפי גרמידי. shema mina ovyah de-ara alfei garmidi. So the
גמרא Gemara says, והא קחזינן דחפרינן פורתא ונפקי מיא, ve-ha ka-chazinan de-chafrinan
purta ve-nafkei maya, but we see that we dig a lot less
than the thousand אמות amot and water comes out. There are wells,
you know, we can dig down and get water out of wells,
not a thousand אמות. amot. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רב
משארשיא ההוא מסומא דפרת. amar Rav Mesharshiya hahu misuma de-Prat. That's from
like the type of
underground channels or arteries that come from the פרת Prat and that's
but the actual תהום, tehom, like the actual core of the תהום
tehom is a thousand אמות. amot. Okay, רש״י Rashi says, רש״י Rashi
explains what this סומא דפרת suma de-Prat is. מעלות עשויים כמחילות שבהם
מי פרת עולים תחת הקרקע. Ma'alot asuyim ke-mechilot she-bahem mei Prat olim
tachat ha-karka. So there's like type of veins in the ground that
the waters of פרת Prat gets closer to the get higher close
to the top of the earth. לפי שפרת גבוה מוצאו מאוד, le-fi
she-Prat gavoha motza'o me'od, because the פרת Prat is very high. כדאמרינן
בבכורות, ked-amrinan bi-Bechorot, because as we say in בכורות, Bechorot, כל הנהרות
למטה מפרת. kol ha-neharot le-mata mi-Prat. So all rivers are below are
below פרת, Prat, you know in terms of height from sea level
I guess. ומים היוצאים מהר גבוה אם דרך מתוקן להם עולים על
הר כיוצא בו ולא יותר. U-mayim ha-yotzim me-har gavoha im derech metukan
lahem olim al har ke-yotzei bo ve-lo yoteir. And waters that come
from a high mountain, if there's like veins for it to go
through, they climb up on a mountain similar to it and no
more. will go up to a similar height. Height. ולפיכך החופרים בהרים
שבבבל הסמוך לפרת מוציאים מים. U'lefichach hachofrim beharim shebeBavel hasamuch lePrat motzi'im
mayim. So you can dig, you know, you can dig in areas
and you'll get water from underground veins that carry the water from
these rivers, but this is not the waters of the תהום. Tehom.
The waters of the תהום Tehom are a thousand אמות Amos below.
Yes.
The פרת Prat is definitely identified as Euphrates?
Yeah, pretty sure or why?
Okay, I was just wondering because it's not obvious.
Yeah, well the letters certainly. והנהר הגדול הוא פרת, Vehanahar hagadol hu
Prat, you know, and the huge river, what was the huge river
in the you know in the ancient world was Euphrates? So anyway,
I mean that was the whole Fertile Crescent.
Or it might have been it might
have been the Nile.
No, but it was clear that it came from the east, like
you know of ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Okay, anyway, so the משנה
Mishna says like, בעי רבי ירמיה. Ba'ei Rabbi Yirmeya. Okay, ועמדו כהנים
בשער העליון שיורד, Ve'amdu kohanim b'sha'ar ha'elyon sheyored, and the כהנים Kohanim
were at the sort of at the opening of the gate that
you know at the top of the steps which would lead into
the עזרת ישראל, Ezrat Yisrael, but they were at the top and
then they started a procession down the steps through the עזרת נשים
Ezrat Nashim and out the front door. And they did it with
their תקיעה תרועה תקיעה, Tekia terua tekia, blowing of the trumpet blasts.
So בעי רבי ירמיה Ba'ei Rabbi Yirmeya asks, למעלה עשרה דנחית חמש
וקאי עשר? Lemala asara d'nachis chamesh v'ka'i esar?
When it says they you know went to the tenth step and
they did the blast, tenth counting from which direction? Okay, is it
the tenth step from the bottom? They had gone down five steps
from the top? או דלמא דנחית עשר וקאי חמש? O dilma d'nachis
esar v'ka'i chamesh?
Or does it mean that they went down ten steps and they
were five steps off from the top? תיקו. Teiku. Well, well, that's
one question we will never know the answer to. תנו רבנן, Tanu
rabbanan, our
rabbis taught. ממה שנאמר ופניהם קדמה. Mimah she'ne'emar upneihem kema. So now
this is you remember how they turned around right before they left
and they said oh we're not like our forefathers who had turned
their backs to this place, we are only to God and would
worship the sun, we are to God and to God is our
eyes. So the verse says, this is a verse in יחזקאל, Yechezkel,
ופניהם קדמה Upneihem kema referring to this sin, that their faces of
the people at the time of the first בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash.
were their faces were to the east. ואין יודע שאחוריהם אל היכל
השם? V'ein yodea she'achoreihem el heichal Hashem? Obviously their backs are to
the היכל, Heichal, right? Because the היכל Heichal is to the west.
So why does it say, אלא מה תלמוד לומר אחוריהם אל היכל
השם? Ela ma talmud lomar achoreihem el heichal Hashem? So why did
the verse say their faces to the east and their back is
to the היכל, Heichal, is to God's house? מלמד שהיו
פורעין עצמן ומתיזין כלפי מעלה. Melamed she'hayu por'in atzman umatrizin klapei mala.
It doesn't just mean their backs, it means their אחור, Achor, it
means their rear ends. And that's what they would do is they
would uncover themselves, expose their rear ends, and they would defecate in
the presence towards God's house. So they would completely not just worship
עבודה זרה Avoda zara but do acts
of disgrace and
defiance towards God's house. ואנו ליה, Ve'anu leYah, but as for us,
our forefathers, we're redeeming אנו, Anu, look at what
we're doing. אנו ליה וליה עינינו. Anu leYah uleYah eineinu. Is that
really true?
ואמר רבי זירא כל האומר שמע שמע כאילו אומר מודים מודים Ve'amar
Rabbi Zeira kol ha'omer shema shema ke'ilu omer modim modim that you
should not say like שמע ישראל Shema Yisrael twice, it's like saying
מודים Modim twice, it suggests a dualism. So how can he say
אנו ליה וליה עינינו, Anu leYah uleYah eineinu, you're saying God's name
twice in a row? So it sounds like a type of a
dualist concern. אלא הכי קאמר, Ela hachi kama, so this is what
they say.
אנו המה משתחוים קדמה, Anu heyma mishtachavim kema, they would bow down
to the east, ואנו ליה, Ve'anu leYah, and we bow down to
God. ועינינו ליה מיחלות, Ve'eineinu leYah meyachalot, and then they would put
a word between the first word of God and the next one.
And our eyes,
for God long for God. So they add another word in between
because חז"ל Chazal does not like the idea that you have two
names of God in juxtaposition. It sounds like
a concern of dualism. And again I just repeat the point I
made before, it's quite interesting all of this dialogue that is going
on, right? It says when they did the ערבה Arava thing, they
would say יופי לך מזבח יופי לך מזבח. Yofi lach mizbe'ach yofi
lach mizbe'ach.
Here they're making before they leave, they're saying look how good we
are as opposed to what our forefathers were. And we've just had
הלל. Hillel הלל was actually the other side of the dialogue. הלל
is embodying God as it were and speaking for God and say,
oh thanks for coming to my house, I'll come to your house,
as long as I'm here everybody is here. So it's fascinating this
whole idea of dialogue that's going on in the context of the
בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. When do you ever have this before?
So something about this idea of סוכות Succos and God's presence and
God's presence in our house that somehow is suggesting this much more
intimate type of a relationship and this actual dialogue. Quite fascinating. Okay.
משנה. Mishna. Now that we've mentioned the תקיעות Tekiot that the כהנים
Kohanim do, we go on to תקיעות Tekiot the general issue of
תקיעות Tekiot in the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash.
אין פוחתין מעשרים ואחת תקיעות במקדש. Ein pochtin m'esrim v'achas tekiot bamikdash.
You have no fewer than 21 תקיעות Tekiot blasts of the חצוצרות
Chatzotzrot in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash Okay,
so every time they would do a תקיעה Tekia it would be
תקיעה תרועה תקיעה. Tekia terua tekia. So really it means seven sets
of תקיעות, Tekiot, because each unit would consist of a תקיעה תרועה
תקיעה. Tekia terua tekia. There's no fewer than 21, i.e. seven, ואין
מוסיפין על ארבעים ושמונה, V'ein mosifin al arbaim u'shmonah, and there'll be
no greater than 48, which is, i.e. 16. בכל יום ויום, be'chol
yom va'yom, now how do you get this? בכל יום ויום היו
שם עשרים ואחת תקיעות, be'chol yom va'yom hayu sham esrim v'achat tkiyos,
normal and
in every day you would have as a the basic would be
the base be 21, seven sets במקדש. ba'mikdash. שלוש בפתיחת שערים, shalosh
bif'tichat shearim,
three when they opened up the gates and they opened up for
business. ותשע לתמיד של שחר, v'tesha l'tamid shel shachar, nine as they
were bringing the morning תמיד, tamid,
meaning so I'm just going to divide by three because it's easier
to think what it would be. It'd be one when they opened
up the gate, three sets when they would do the תמיד. tamid.
Now when is it when they would do the תמיד? tamid? If
you take a look at רש"י, Rashi תשע לתמיד של שחר, tesha
l'tamid shel shachar, רש"י says תשעה כשהיו מנסכין את נסכי התמיד, tishah
k'shehayu menaschin es nischei hatamid, when they were poured the wine libation,
and then we learned before that that's when the לויים Levi'im would
sing and do the musical instruments. הלויים אומרים שיר, ha'Levi'im omrim shir,
ושלשה פרקים היו בשיר, u'shlosha prakim hayu ba'shir, and there were three
breaks in the song שהיו מפסיקין בו ותוקעין הכהנים בחצוצרות ומשתחווים
העם. shehayu mafsikin bo v'tokin ha'kohanim ba'chatzotzros u'mishtachavim ha'am. Okay, so that's
quite fascinating the choreography there. The לויים Levi'im would play the musical
instruments but the חצוצרות chatzotzros were for the כהנים, kohanim, so in
the middle of the singing and the music and all that beautiful
thing during the pouring of the wine, you'd have a break, you'd
have תקיעה tkiyah of yes the blowing of trumpets, and then the
people would actually go ahead and and bow down. So it would
be a way of getting like more you know participation. It wouldn't
all just be a spectator sport. Like some people love חזנות, chazzanus,
for me it turns דאוונינג davening into a spectator sport, right? So
here you get both, you get like the beautiful whatever but then
you break and everybody you know bows down and you have the
blast and it's a little more participatory. Okay, now, so that's, so
you would have three of that during the תמיד של שחר, tamid
shel shachar, so now we're up to four sets.
ותשע לתמיד של בין הערביים, v'tesha l'tamid shel bein ha'arbayim, similarly you
do the same thing for the afternoon תמיד. tamid. So now we're
up to, that's your full so that's three more sets, so you're
up to seven, that's your total seven sets, so that's your 21.
Okay, so that's your standard 21. ובמוספין היו מוסיפין עוד תשע, uv'musafin
hayu mosifin od tesha, and if you had a מוסף musaf then
you would do because you have the you'd have the you'd have
another nine because you do also the wine libation at the מוסף
musaf and the song of לויים Levi'im at the מוסף, musaf, so
that would be any time you would have that whole singing along
with the קרבנות korbanos which would be by these you know by
these obligatory קרבנות korbanos you would have the musical instruments and you'd
have the breaks by the by the חצוצרות. chatzotzros. Okay, so normally
you get it, you get basically when you do the wine libations
that come with the communal obligatory קרבנות korbanos you have the singing
and the musical instruments, and with the singing and the musical instruments
you get these breaks in it by the blowing of the trumpets
with the bowing down. So a normal day there's one for the
opening of the gates, three and three is you know for each
for the תמיד של שחר, tamid shel shachar, תמיד של בין הערביים,
tamid shel bein ha'arbayim, and by time when there's a מוסף musaf
there's another three with the מוסף. musaf.
Okay, yes, in Jerusalem on ערב שבת Erev Shabbos they blow the
the siren, I wonder...
keep keep let's keep on listening, you're good anticipation.
Okay, ובערב שבת, uv'erev shabbat, so now we're up to in a
normal like יום טוב Yom Tov you would have 24, okay, not
24, you'd have 3, 3, 3, 9, 10, you'd have 30.
ובערב שבת, uv'erev shabbat, is my dividing by three confusing for you?
because it's to be it's
helpful...
no but it's just easier for me to think about the different
moment you know sets. Okay, ובערב שבת היו מוסיפין שש, uv'erev shabbat
hayu mosifin sheish, six more, meaning what why? Meaning two more sets.
שלש להבטיל את העם ממלאכה, shalosh l'havtil es ha'am mi'melacha, so as
they were saying you'd do three to say it's about to be
sunset so you'd have the blasts and presumably it was they were
probably they would do it with torches you know one person lights
a torch from a distant mountains, so if they're blowing the blast
in the בית המקדש there's some relay system that that blast gets
communicated throughout the city. Okay, so to let people know it's about
to be שבת Shabbos they would do one. ושלש, v'shalosh, and another
three or another set להבדיל בין קודש לחול l'havdil bein kodesh l'chol
when it was not just like 40 minutes before but when it
was 2 minutes before to indicate that it's about to be שבת.
Shabbos. Okay, interesting use of the phrase להבדיל l'havdil when you're going
from חול chol into קודש, kodesh, but it's the same point to
make that separation. Okay, ערב שבת שבתוך החג, erev shabbat she'betoch he'chag,
so now if let's say you had the combination of these two
circumstances, it was ערב שבת Erev Shabbos and it was in the
middle of
סוכות. Succos. היו שם ארבעים ושמונה, hayu sham arbaim u'shmonah, that's when
you could get your full 48, 16 sets. Let's figure it out.
שלש לפתיחת שערים, shalosh lif'tichat shearim, one for the three i.e. one
set for the opening of the gates, שלש לשער העליון ושלש לשער
התחתון shalosh l'shaar ha'elyon v'shalosh l'shaar hatachton
because you would also have now not just for the opening of
the gates in the first thing in the morning, you would also
have it for when you're going and
the
whole...
Right, here's the
עזרת ישראל *Ezrat Yisrael*.
Here's your
steps. Five, six, seven, eight. Getting worse. Okay, here's your עזרת נשים
*Ezrat Nashim*. So, right, and the כהנים *Kohanim* started here with the
trumpet. Here's the upper gate. Anyway, the לווים *Levites* were standing here.
They walked out and did a procession. Then they blew it again
here as they walked שער העליון ושער התחתון *Sha'ar haElyon v'Sha'ar haTachton*.
So now going out of the בית המקדש *Beis haMikdash*. Then they
go wherever they go to draw the water. And now as they're
going to draw the water,
right, as they're going to draw the water, they do another set
of שופר *shofar* blasts. Okay, so they do a whole procession. Okay,
so שלוש לשער העליון ושלש לשער התחתון *Shloish l'Sha'ar haElyon v'Shloish l'Sha'ar
haTachton*, שלוש למילוי המים *Shloish l'miluy hamayim*, three when they drew the
water, ושלש על גבי המזבח *v'Shloish al gabi hamizbeach*, and three when
they poured the water, accompanying the actual pouring of the water. תשע
לתמיד של שחר *Tesha l'Tamid shel Shachar* ותשע לתמיד של בין הערביים
*v'tesha l'Tamid shel Bein Ha'arbayim* ותשע למוספים *v'tesha l'musafim*. And then you
have the תמיד *Tamid*, the three sets, nine, three sets by תמיד
של שחר *Tamid shel Shachar*, תמיד של בין הערביים *Tamid shel Bein
Ha'arbayim*, and the מוסף *Musaf*. And שלש *Shloish* plus one plus if
it's also ערב שבת *Erev Shabbos*, then you have three more לבטל
את העם ממלאכה *l'vatel et ha'am mimelacha*, to warn people to stop
doing מלאכה *melacha*, ושלש *v'Shloish* and three when it's about to be
שבת *Shabbos*, להבדיל בין קודש לחול *l'havdil bein kodesh l'chol*. So let's
see if we count that in terms of individual units. Okay, we've
got one unit when we open up the gate, one here when
they start the procession, so three here. Start the procession, go out
the door, do the filling. So that's four. Then they're going to
do one unit when they pour the water, that's five. Okay, then
they're going to do three units of the three different קרבנות *korbanot*,
תמיד של שחר *Tamid shel Shachar*, מוסף *Musaf*, תמיד של בין הערביים
*Tamid shel Bein Ha'arbayim*. That's nine, that's fourteen. And then because it's
ערב שבת *Erev Shabbos*, they're going to do one to warn the
people to stop doing מלאכה *melacha*, one when it's actually about to
be שבת *Shabbos*, that's sixteen. 16 times 3 is 48. There you
go. Now of course what's interesting is, you know what it doesn't
mention? It doesn't mention the תקיעה תרועה תקיעה Tekiah Teruah Tekiah, *tekiah-teruah-tekiah*
that they, that it says they did when they did the ערבה
*Aravah*, right? It says they did תקיעה תרועה תקיעה Tekiah Teruah Tekiah
*tekiah-teruah-tekiah* when they did the ערבה *Aravah*, didn't it? That's what I
remembered. So I don't
know, we can go check. I'm pretty sure it said that. מצות
ערבה כיצד *Mitzvat Aravah keitzad*? Yeah. And it says after they stuck
it by the side of the altar, תקעו והריעו ותקעו *taku v'heriu
v'taku*. So if הושענא רבה *Hoshanah Rabbah* fell out on this day
of ערב שבת *Erev Shabbos*, that would get you, I don't know,
I don't know why it would get you three more. Anyway, okay.
להבדיל בין קודש לחול *l'havdil bein kodesh l'chol*.
Okay, so now the גמרא *Gemara* says as follows: מתניתין דלא כרבי
יהודה K'Rabbi Yehuda. *Matnisin d'lo k'Rabbi Yehuda*. Our mishnah is not like
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda*. דתניא *detanya*, we taught in a
ברייתא *Braita*, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda אומר הפוחת לא יפחות משבע והמוסיף
לא יוסיף על שש עשרה *Rabbi Yehuda omer hapocheis lo yifchos misheva
v'hamosif lo yosif al sheish esreh*. So he says that there's a
minimum of seven and a maximum of sixteen. So he did the
counting the way I was doing because it makes it easier. The
units, counting a unit as one, not as three. But the גמרא
*Gemara* understands that it's not just a counting number, it's not just
a label, there's actually a real difference between them. במאי קמיפלגי *bimai
kamifligi*? What's the debate? רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda סבר תקיעה תרועה Tekiah
Teruah תקיעה Tekiah אחת היא *Rabbi Yehuda savar tekiah-teruah-tekiah achas hi*, that
that's one unit. ורבנן סברי תקיעה Tekiah לחוד ותרועה לחוד *v'Rabbanan savari
tekiah lachud u-teruah lachud*, that they're separate units. Okay, now the real
issue here is could be a question of whether you take a
breath between the תקיעה Tekiah. תרועה Teruah. תקיעה *tekiah-teruah-tekiah* or not. Meaning,
not just out of convenience count it one or count it three,
but how many real distinct sounds are you going to make? Separate
sounds are you going to make? מאי טעמא דרבי
יהודה *mai ta'ama d'Rabbi Yehuda*? What's the reason of רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda*? אמר קרא ותקעתם תרועה Teruah *amar kra utkatem teruah*,
and then there's a question on the side that says אלמא תרועה
Teruah ותקיעה אחת היא *alma teruah u-tekiah achas hi*. If he uses
the verb blow a תרועה *teruah*, but the verb is תקיעה *tekiah*,
you see that it's one unit. It has to be all one
unit. ורבנן *v'Rabbanan*, and the rabbis would say ההוא לפשוטה לפניה ולאחריה
הוא דאתא *hahu l'pishuta lifneyha u-le'achareyha hu d'ata*. No,
it's telling you a תקיעה *tekiah* precedes a תרועה *teruah*, but it's
not telling you it's one unit.
Okay, so ורבנן מאי טעמייהו *v'Rabbanan mai ta'amai*? Where do the rabbis
get an idea that they're distinct units? דכתיב ובהקהיל את הקהל תתקעו
ולא תריעו *d'chtiv u-v'hakheel et hakahal titke'u v'lo tari'u*. So the תורה
*Torah* allows for a phenomenon of a תקיעה *tekiah* independent of a
תרועה *teruah*. So you see it exists as an independent sound. ואי
סלקא דעתך תקיעה תרועה אחת היא *v'ei salka daitach tekiah-teruah achas hi*,
if you think it's basically one sound. So I mean not one
sound like it's the same throughout, but there's no break between the
sounds. ואי סלקא דעתך תקיעה תרועה אחת היא *v'ei salka daitach tekiah-teruah
achas hi*, אמר רחמנא פלגא דמצוה עביד
ופלגא לא עביד *amar Rachmana palga d'mitzvah avid u-palga lo avid*? How
could the תורה *Torah* say do half of a note and not
a full note? Obviously it's distinct and even when you do תקיעה
תרועה תקיעה *tekiah-teruah-tekiah* you have a break between the sounds.
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi
Yehuda*, and רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* would say, yeah, the תורה *Torah*
could say half a sound. ההוא לסימנא בעלמא הוא דאתא *hahu l'simana
b'alma hu d'ata*. That's just as a
way of getting That doesn't bother me. For רבנן, Rabanan, סימנו Simanu
is almost a sign, we're doing it as a way of getting
people's attention, but ורחמנא שוויה מצוה, Verachmana Shavye Mitzvah, but the Torah
said fine, but this is the way you get people's attention is
you do this sound so that means that this sound has some
independent standing. Okay, so again it's clear the context of the emphasis
for the גמרא פשוט Pashut is not just a question of numbering,
it's a question about do you take breaks between them, do you
make it into or is it conceptually one sound or is it
conceptually distinct sounds. So let's go and now let's just end it
with this last line. כמאן אזלא הא דאמר רב כהנא, Keman azla
ha d'amar Rav Kahana, who is going like this statement of רב
כהנא? Rav Kahana? אין בין תקיעה לתרועה ולא כלום, Ein bein tekiah
l'teruah v'lo klum, you don't take any there's absolutely no pause between
a תקיעה and a תרועה. כמאן? Keman? כרבי יהודה. That's going like
רבי יהודה because that's exactly his point that it's all one sound.
פשיטא Pshita says the גמרא, obviously! No, מהו דתימא Ma d'teima I
might have thought אפילו כרבנן, Afilu k'Rabanan, maybe it goes like the
רבנן, Rabanan ולאפוקי מדרבי יוחנן U'l'afukei mid'Rabbi Yochanan and it's coming to
reject רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and doesn't mean that there's that there's
no pause between them. What it means is what they're trying to
say is something different, they're trying to reject רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
דאמר שמע תשע תקיעות בתשע שעות ביום יצא. D'amar shama tesha tekiot
b'tesha shaot hayom yatza. He says on ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah if
you hear the nine תקיעות, Tekiot, because minimally we know if we
knew what a תרועה was you would be enough to have three
sets of תקיעה תרועה תקיעה, and if you heard each one at
a different hour you'd be יצא. Yotza. So obviously that's like a
big, it's one thing to say you have to do it as
תקיעה תרועה תקיעה without a break at all. It's another thing to
say no, you have a break, but not only do you have
a break, but you can actually hear them an hour apart from
one another. So maybe when it says don't break between תקיעה תרועה
it's not saying like רבי יהודה that you do it literally without
a break. What it's trying to say is you can't have a
huge break between them.
קמשמע לן, Kamashma Lan, so therefore we're telling you no, this statement
of no interruption is רבי יהודה's statement. It's not the way the
רבנן Rabanan would argue and say you don't need that you're not
allowed to have a huge break. So the גמרא says אימא הכי
נמי, Eima hachi nami, no maybe that was a good point, maybe
that is what they're saying. Maybe they're saying don't have a huge
break between them, but maybe it's not saying you can't have any
break. No, the גמרא says אם כן מאי ולא כלום. Im ken
mai v'lo klum. So no, then it would just say don't break,
but it says don't break ולא כלום, v'lo klum, there can be
no break, not even the tiniest break. So you see that is
the רבי יהודה position. So there are three logical positions. רבי יהודה
who says it's all basically halakhically one sound and you don't even
pause between תקיעה and the תרועה and the תקיעה. You have the
רבנן that say they're distinct sounds and you have a break, a
moment's pause between them, but maybe still they have to be in
tight juxtaposition, exactly how tight is not clear. And then you have
the statement of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that takes it to an
extreme, says they're distinct sounds, they don't even have to be a
group of sounds, they could be nine at nine different hours of
the day.
So it's basically is it one sound, is it three sounds but
a grouping and they would have to be tightly juxtaposed, or is
it ממש Mamash distinct sounds and could be over many hours of
the day. Okay, and we finished.